Okay today's דף *Daf* is בבא קמא *Bava Kamma* י"א *Yud Aleph*,
11. We pick up on י' עמוד ב' *Yud Amud Bet* and
the two dots, the very last of the narrow lines.
And our learning should be in the זכות *Zechut* of the safety
of our חיילים *Chayalim* and חיילות *Chayallot* and a speedy end to
the fighting and for a quick resolution and the safety and security
of עם ישראל *Am Yisrael* מדינת ישראל *Medinat Yisrael*. Okay, so we
pick up on the last of the narrow lines on י' עמוד
ב' *Yud Amud Bet*. חבתי בתשלומי נזקו *Chavti Betashlumei Nizko*. This is
the משנה *Mishna* that speaks about the common denominator between the אבות
נזיקין nizikin, *Avot Nezikin* and it says that when you are liable,
you have incurred the liability of תשלומי נזקו *Tashlumei Nizko*, of paying
for the damages. So let's see what the גמרא gemara *Gemara* does
with that. חבתי בנזקו לא קתני *Chavti Benizko Lo Katanei*. The משנה
*Mishna* didn't say I am liable for the damages, אלא בתשלומי נזקו
*Ella Betashlumei Nizko*, for the
compensation of the damages. So okay, what are we going to make
out of that? תנינא tanina, להא דתנו רבנן *Tanina Lahada Detanu Rabbanan*.
We taught in the משנה *Mishna* that which we taught in a
ברייתא *Beraita*. תשלומי נזק nezek, *Tashlumei Nezek*, what does the phrase תשלומי
נזק *Tashlumei Nezek*, the Tanna-itic phrase mean? מלמד שהבעלים מטפלין בנבילה *Melamed
Shehabealim Metaplin Beniveila*. That teaches you that the
owners, the owners of the cow that gored, it's their responsibility to
worry about the carcass of their animal. All right, so a bull
gored their cow, which was worth $100 and now the cow, the
dead carcass, is worth $10.
So they, the owner of the bull, has to pay for $90
of damage and not it's not you break it, you buy it.
It's not that he now owns the dead carcass and has to
pay for the $100 bull.
No, he caused a $100 cow to now be a $10 carcass.
He pays $90 and the owner continues to own the dead carcass,
the $10 dead carcass. מלמד שהבעלים מטפלין בנבילה *Melamed Shehabealim Metaplin Beniveila*.
The owners of the cow have to take care of, have to
be responsible for the carcass. מנא הני מילי *Mina Hani Milei*? Where
does this come from? Maybe you'd have to pay, maybe the owner
of the bull would have to pay the full $100 and he
would take the dead carcass. אמר רבי אמי דאמר קרא *Amar Rabbi
Ami Damar Kra*, the פסוק pasuk. *Pasuk* says מכה נפש בהמה ישלמנה
*Makeh Nefesh Behemah Yeshalmena*, one who smites the soul of an animal,
a person who kills an animal, shall pay for it. אל תקרי
ישלמנה אלא ישלימנה *Al Tikrei Yeshalmena Ella Yashlimena*, shall pay for it,
shall complete, supplement the damage. So if somebody killed a cow, let's
say now it's a person who killed a cow and it was
worth 100 and now it's worth 10, it's not he shall pay
for the cow, he shall pay the 100, no, he shall supplement
the difference of what it was worth then and what it's worth
now, he shall pay 90. And the logic of this is that
it's not you break it, you buy it. It's not for sale,
you didn't buy it. You damaged something, you pay for the damage
that your actions brought about, the lesser value of the thing now,
but the thing itself remains in the ownership of the original owner.
Okay, אל תקרי ישלמנה אלא ישלימנה *Al Tikrei Yeshalmena Ella Yashlimena*. רב
כהנא Rav Kahana אמר מהכא *Rav Kahana Amar Meihacha*, רב כהנא Rav
Kahana *Rav Kahana* says another פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* we can learn it
from. אם טרוף יטרף יביאהו עד yevi'eihu ed, הטרפה לא
ישלם *Im Tarof Yitaref Yivieihu Ed Hatereifah Lo Yeshalem*. So this is
talking about somebody who was watching an animal, a שומר shomer *Shomer*,
and if the animal
got devoured by a wild animal, then he shall go ahead and
pay for the,
he has to pay for the damage, well actually the פסוק pasuk
*Pasuk* says הטרפה לא ישלם *Hatereifah Lo Yeshalem*, he does not pay
for the damages. It's a hard פסוק pasuk. *Pasuk* to read exactly
what יביאהו עד *Yivieihu Ed* means, but let's see what the גמרא
gemara *Gemara* does with this. If the person was a שואל shoel
*Sho'el*, for example, he would pay for it or if it happened
and the animal was devoured and it wasn't an אונס *Oness*, there
was a degree of negligence, then he would pay for the animal
as a שומר shomer *Shomer*.
And
יביאהו עד הטרפה ישלם *Yivieihu Ad Hatereifah Yeshalem*, not עד *Ed*, he
shall pay up
to the value of the dead
animal. טרפה עצמה לא ישלם *Tereifah Atzmah Lo Yeshalem*. So the difference
between the 100 and the 10 he pays for 90, but for
the dead animal, the carcass, he's not paying for that, that still
remains the owner's. חזקיה אמר מהכא *Chizkiyah Amar Meihacha*, חזקיה *Chizkiyah* says
from the following פסוק pasuk *Pasuk*: והמת vehamet יהיה לו לניזק *Vahamet
Yihiyeh Lo Lanizak*. That's when an ox gores a cow and it
says שלם ישלם שור תחת השור shor tachat hashor *Shallem Yeshalem Shor
Tachat Hashor*, you should pay
an ox for an ox, שלם ישלם שור תחת השור shor tachat
hashor והמת יהיה לו *Shallem Yeshalem Shor Tachat Hashor Vahamet Yihiyeh Lo*
and you get the dead body. So that actually directly deals with
our case. Now, what is it saying? Who is the יהיה לו
*Yihiyeh Lo*? Who is the one that gets the actual carcass? So
we are reading it as המת יהיה לו לניזק. hamet yihiyeh lo
lenizak. It means that the damaged party so get the carcass and
the damager, the one with the goring ox, he only pays for
the loss of value. Now that is not necessarily the פשט pshat
of the פסוק. pasuk The פשט pshat of the פסוק is שור
תחת השור shor tachat hashor you pay you get exactly the פשט
pshat of the פסוק is you break it you buy it. You
pay for the entire ox that got killed and you the damager
you take home the dead animal. המת יהיה לו. hamet yihiyeh lo.
Pay for the whole ox, you take home the dead animal. You
broke it you bought it. Okay, but that is not the way
this is being read. This is being read pay for the damage
you created and והמת the carcass that remains with the original owner.
Okay, המת יהיה לו hamet yihiyeh lo, לניזק. אתה אומר לניזק או
אינו אלא למזיק? ata omer lenizak o eino ela lamazik? Now maybe
it means like we thought. You know, no, the מזיק, mazik, you
take the carcass and pay for the full ox, for the full
dead ox. אמרת לא כך היה. amarta lo kach haya. The answer
is, no, that's not what it means. So the גמרא Gemara says,
מאי לא כך היה? mai lo kach haya? What do you mean
no that's not what it means? It was a reasonable read of
the פסוק. What's the response? אמר אביי אי סלקא דעתך נבילה דמזיק
הויא. amar abayei ei salka daitach neveila demazik havya.
No, if you were to read the פסוק to mean that the
מזיק, mazik, the goring ox owner, is the one that has to
take the dead carcass, לכתוב רחמנא שור תחת שור ולשתוק. lichtov rachmana
shor tachat shor velishtok. It should have been simpler. It said you
shall pay an ox for an ox, and I would have understood
it meant pay for the entire ox and take home the dead
carcass. Okay,
ולשתוק. velishtok. והמת יהיה לו למה לי? vehamet yihiyeh lo lama li?
Why did it have to say and the carcass will be his?
שמע מינה דלניזק. shma mina dlenizak. It's telling you that that it
actually means not the simple meaning of pay for the full ox,
pay for the full ox once you once you accept the idea
that the ניזק, nizak, the damagee, the owner, he still has the
dead the carcass, and then you pay for the difference that you
created. Of course, still it's a that becomes a very hard read
of שור תחת השור shor tachat hashor which sounds like the full
ox. But anyway the גמרא Gemara, is saying that שור תחת השור
itself would have told me that you the מזיק mazik take the
dead carcass, since it then goes further and says המת יהיה לו,
hamet yihiyeh lo rather than seeing it as reinforcing the simple meaning
of the words שור תחת השור we're seeing it actually as modifying
it and saying that the המת יהיה לו means that the original
owner keeps the carcass and you only pay the difference.
Okay, וצריכא. utzricha. And you need it now to have been said
in all of those three scenarios. One was a case of a
person damaging a cow, the other was about a שומר shomer whose
the cow got you know torn up by a wild animal and
the third was an ox goring a cow or an ox, an
ox goring an ox. וצריכא. utzricha. You need all three. דאי כתב
רחמנא מכה בהמה ישלמנה משום דלא שכיחא. de'i katav rachmana makeh behema
yeshalmena mishum dlo shchicha. If it was talking about the case of
a person damaging, you know, killing a cow, that's a very rare
case. Person would willingly go ahead and kill a cow. So in
that case, you know, because it's rare, the תורה torah did not
put the you know went easier on the מזיק. mazik. It's funny
why is it rare it goes easier but okay. And
it said the ניזק nizak still owns the dead carcass, the מזיק
mazik only pays the difference. Okay, אבל טריפה דשכיחא. aval tereifa deshchicha.
But a case about watching an animal that some wild animal came
and and you know and tore at it and killed it, that's
a more common case and maybe if it's more common the תורה
torah should try to be a little more sensitive to the loss
that's being incurred by the owner of the cow. אימא לא. eima
lo. Maybe that therefore the owner the the the ניזק, nizak, the
owner of the cow, would not have to worry about the carcass.
Let the שומר shomer pay for everything. צריכא. tzricha. So it needed
to tell me that case. ואי אשמעינן טריפה. ve'i ashmeinan tereifa. If
it had just said the case about the שומר shomer that you
have to that that's the responsibility of the owner to deal with
the carcass. משום דממילא. mishum demimeila. That's because okay at the end
of the day the שומר shomer. was just passively negligent. So we'll
go a little easy on him and we'll let the owner worry
about the carcass. אבל
מכה בהמה. aval makeh behema. But when a human being intentionally kills
an animal, בידיים, beyadayim, it's doing it directly as an act of
damage. אימא לא. eima lo. It shouldn't go easy on the guilty
party, on the damaging party, and therefore in that case it should
be the מזיק mazik who has to worry about the dead carcass.
צריכא. tzricha. So therefore and it had to tell me both of
those cases. One case even though it's rare it's still the obligation
is on excuse me.
One case even though it's בידיים, beyadayim, it's still the obligation is
on the is on the damaged I mean is on the ניזק.
nizak. And on the other case even though it's a common case,
the שומר shomer case, also nevertheless the I think I said that
wrong. Let's say that again. Okay, it has to tell me both
cases. It has to tell me the case of the person destroying
it בידיים, beyadayim, even though I might have thought that you would
go easy on the damager because it's rare, nevertheless that doesn't matter.
And it has to tell me the case of the שומר. shomer,
I might have thought you would go easier on the שומר shomer
because it's not direct and even so that case also.
All right, I think I said that wrong again. Let's try that
one more time. Okay, even in a case where it's common like
the case of the שומר, shomer the responsibility of the dead animal
is on the owner, and even in a case when it is
בידיים, biyadim, like the case of a person directly destroying an animal,
the responsibility is on the owner. So even in the cases where
the damaging party has more sort of reason to make them obligated,
we nevertheless the responsibility for the נבילה nevelah is on the owner.
Okay, so that's why it needed those two cases. ואשמעינן הני תרתי,
V'atshminan hanei tarti, if it had just said those
two, האי משום דלא שכיחא hai mishum delo shechicha והאי משום דממילא,
v'hai mishum d'mimmeyla, maybe each one of them though, the reason the
Torah is going easy is because each one of them has a
reason to be a little bit sympathetic. One it's true that it's
common, but nevertheless it's not בידיים, biyadim, and the other, it's true
it's בידיים, biyadim, but nevertheless it's rare, so maybe that's why the
Torah was going easy. המציא לו, Aval hamesia lo, but in the
case about an ox goring another ox, דשכיחא, deshchicha, it's both
common ובידיים u'biyadim and it was a direct act of מזיק, mazik,
the ox gored the other ox, in that case where it has
both of those bad things, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe we would
put the responsibility on the מזיק, mazik, so it had to tell
me even that case, responsibility is on the owner. ואשמעינן המציא לו,
V'atshminan hamesia lo, and if it had just started saying the case
of the ox goring the ox, that the responsibility is on the
owner, משום דממונא כמזיק, mishum demamona kamazik, at the end of the
day, that's your property that's damaging, it's not you personally that's doing
the damage.
אבל הכא דבגופיה מזיק, Aval hacha d'begufa mazik, but when you personally
do the damage, either as a שומר shomer, passively, or actively as
an אדם המזיק, adam hamazik, I might think that in those cases
you, the מזיק, mazik, have responsibility, צריכא, tzricha, it had to tell
you. All right, so it had to tell you in all these
three cases, whether it's you doing it as an אדם המזיק adam
hamazik or as a שומר shomer or your ox doing it, whether
it's common or rare, whether it's בידיים biyadim or ממילא, mimmeyla, in
all those cases, doesn't matter, the responsibility is on the ניזק. nizak.
Doesn't seem so nice to the poor ניזק nizak who's the injured
party, okay, but conceptually you understand it because you're paying for the
damage created and therefore you don't pay for the whole animal, you
pay for the damage you caused, which is the original value minus
the current value. Why should you have to go ahead and take
a carcass that isn't your carcass, isn't from your animal? Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר ליה רב כהנא לרב, Amlei Rav
Kahana l'Rav, so Rav Kahana said to
Rav, אלא טעמא דכתב רחמנא והמציא לו, ella taama deketav rachmana v'hamsia
lo, the reason we know this idea that בעלים מטפלין בנבילה baalim
metaplin benevelah is because the Torah says that the carcass is his,
and that we understand the carcass means the ניזק, nizak, the original
owner. הא לאו הכי, Ha lav hacha, had it not said that,
הוה אמינא נבילה למזיק, hava amina nevelah l'mazik, I would have said
if it had not been for all these פסוקים, pesukim, I would
have said you damage somebody's cow, you have to take the carcass
and pay them for the whole value of the cow. Okay, he
said, even if that were true, why couldn't you just turn around
and use the carcass as part of the payment? השתא אי אית
ליה לדידיה כמה טריפות יהיב ליה, Hashta ee is lei ledidey kamma
treifos yahiv lei, let's say the guy who is the damager, let's
say Reuven's ox gored Shimon's cow and now Shimon's cow is worth
ten. So if Reuven happens to have a storehouse of animal carcasses,
so he could
give Shimon ten animal carcasses to pay for his
hundred dollar cow, דאמר מר, d'amar mar, ישיב לרבות שוה כסף אפילו
סובין, yashiv l'rabbos shaveh kessef afilu subbin, it says you shall return
and this teaches us something we taught from way at the beginning,
that you can pay even like dross, even
paper clips, any type of object of value can be paid in
a payment of a debt for having caused damage. So therefore says
the גמרא, Gemara. I don't understand why any of this matters. Going
spending all of this time to say that he only owes him
90 and he doesn't owe him 100 but he gets to take
home the carcass. Let's say he owed him 100 and he got
to take home the carcass. Turn around and give the carcass back
and that's the first ten dollars. You can pay the damaged party
with anything. So what difference does it make who gets the carcass?
דידיה מיבעיא So didey mibaya? Obviously he could start by paying him
with the carcass that originally began to was owned by Shimon. So
what's the point of saying Shimon has to keep the carcass and
Reuven only owes him 90 dollars? Let Reuven owe him 100 dollars
and the first ten dollars is the carcass.
לא נצרכא, No, nitzrecha, here's why you need
it, אלא לפחת נבילה, ella lephat nevelah, for the depreciation of the
carcass. Because when does Shimon start, when does Reuven start start paying
שמעון Shimon, *Shimon*. When they come to court and the court says,
oh, okay, it was a damage of, you know, I don't know,
let's say they said the whole value of the cow, they came
to court they said it was a value of $100 and go
ahead and you now owe him $100. And ראובן Reuven, *Reuven*, let's
say the הלכה halacha? *halacha* was, owned the carcass. So at the
moment that the the animal was gored and died, the carcass was
worth 10, but now that it finally is time for him to
pay, the carcass has continued to depreciate, פחת נבילה pchat neveila, *p'chas
neveilah* and is worth 5. So he goes around and he hands
it to שמעון *Shimon*, he's only paid $5. But if we say
from the very outset that ראובן Reuven *Reuven* only owed $90, so
then if if the value of the carcass goes down, שמעון *Shimon*
is going to suffer that loss and ראובן Reuven *Reuven* from the
very beginning owes $90. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says there is
a conceptual difference if ראובן Reuven *Reuven* owes $100 and owns the
carcass
or owes $90. Okay, and the just conceptually it's different and you
know but but practically it'll play out if the carcass changes in
value, okay, if he owes him 100 and the carcass changes in
value, then that change in value which most likely will be going
down in value will be incurred by ראובן *Reuven*. If he owes
him 90, any change of value would be incurred by שמעון *Shimon*.
So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, לימא פחת נבילה
תנאי היא *leima p'chas neveilah tanna'i hi*. Let's say this issue of
who has to incur the cost of the going down of the
value, let's say that's a מחלוקת תנאים *machlokes tanna'im*, meaning also which
is another way of saying this very principle of whether you owe
90 or 100. Okay, who owns the נבילה *neveilah*? דתניא *Detanya*, we
taught in a ברייתא *braisa*, exactly on this פסוק *pasuk* which is
one of the sources of our teaching. אם טרף יטרף יבאהו עד
*Im tarof yitaref yevi'eihu ed*, last line of י"א עמוד ב' yud
aleph amud bet, *Yud Aleph Amud Beis* now we start with י"א
עמוד א' *Yud Aleph Amud Aleph*, okay, if it is torn up
you should bring עד *ed*, let's see what it literally means a
witness, let's see how this is read.
So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues on the top of י"א
עמוד א' *Yud Aleph Amud Aleph*. יביא עדים שנטרפה באונס ופטור *Yavi
edim shenitrefa b'onnes upatur*. So what it means is that's the simple
sense of the פסוק *pasuk* הטרפה לא ישלם *hatreifah lo yeshalem*. This
is a שומר שכר shomer sachar *shomer sachar*. So it says if
he can bring עד *ed*, testimony, that it was not it was
that the wild animals attacked and it was due to not even
a tiny negligence of his own, it was complete אונס *onnes*, completely
out of his control, then he is exempt. Okay, simple הלכה halacha
*halacha* that a שומר shomer, שכר *shomer sachar* is exempt when it's
an אונס *onnes*. That's reading number one. אבא Abba שאול אומר יביא
אדודא לבית דין *Abba Shaul omer yavi adudah l'beis din*. No, יבאהו
עד *yevi'eihu ed*, עד *ed* here means אדודא *adudah* which is like
the you know the carcass or there's different reads, you know תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafos* has a read ארורה *arurah*, the cursed, you know dead
animal, but anyway, bring the dead animal to the בית דין beit
din *beis din*. Meaning and therefore pay let the בית דין beit
din *beis din* determine how much the carcass is worth and you
the מזיק mazik, *mazik* have to pay the difference. So reading אבא
Abba שאול *Abba Shaul* to say this principle like we had talked
before that the ניזק *nizak* has to deal with the נבילה *neveilah*.
מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי *Mai lav b'ha kamiflegi*, this must be the
debate. מר סבר פחת נבילה דניזק pchat neveila d'nizak, הוי *Mar savar
p'chas neveilah d'nizak havei*, it's going in the reverse order. אבא Abba
שאול *Abba Shaul* would understand that פחת נבילה *p'chas neveilah* is the
ניזק *nizak*, the מזיק mazik *mazik* only pays the בית דין beit
din *beis din* assesses the value of the carcass and the מזיק
mazik *mazik* pays the difference. ומר סבר דמזיק הוי *Umar savar d'mazik
havei* and אבא Abba שאול *Abba Shaul* who doesn't read the פסוק
*pasuk* that way would say no, actually the מזיק mazik *mazik* is
חייב chayav *chayav* the full 100. Yes he can use the נבילה
*neveilah* to pay, but it starts with fundamentally he's חייב chayav *chayav*
the full 100 and it's his נבילה *neveilah*. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says לא דכולי עלמא דניזק *lo d'chuli alma d'nizak*. No, no,
no, we're going to try to insist that everybody agrees to our
teaching that you only are obligated in the difference and that the
original owner stays owns retains ownership over the carcass. דכולי עלמא דניזק
*D'chuli alma d'nizak*. והכא בטורח נבילה קמיפלגי *V'hacha b'torach neveilah kamiflegi*. And
the issue here meaning you know what אבא שאול *Abba Shaul* is
being sort of מחדש *mechadesh*, you know that the תנא tanna, קמא
*tanna kamma* is not buying into, is the question of who has
to bring the נבילה *neveilah* to the בית דין *beis din*. You
know this happened out in the field and now you got to
go ahead and you got to like if בית דין *beis din*
has to assess it, you got to shlep the נבילה *neveilah* to
the בית דין *beis din*, that's אבא שאול *Abba Shaul*'s language, יביא
אדודא לבית דין *yavi adudah l'beis din*. Okay, or we'll see in
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, you know you might have to bring it
from the field to the city if you wanted to sell it
and get some and get you know get some cash for it,
so who has the responsibility to shlep it into the city? דתניא
*Detanya* as we taught in a ברייתא *braisa*, דתניא *hatanya* here is
not a question but it's a support, אחרים אומרים מניין שעל בעל
הבור להעלות השור מבורו *acheirim omrim minayin she'al ba'al habor l'haalosos hashor
miboro*, how do you know that the מזיק *mazik* the owner of
the well is the one that has to bring the the dead
animal out of the well? Okay, even though the dead animal belongs
to the ניזק *nizak* and you it's you the one who did
the damage that have to bring it out of the well to
get to a place where it could be sold to somebody else.
How do you know that? תלמוד לומר כסף ישיב לבעליו והמת *Talmud
lomar kesef yashiv l'ba'alav v'hameis*. Money he should pay back to the
owner and the dead. So meaning and the dead also he has
to bring back to the owner he has to make it something
that can be used in something that can be sold. So that's
what אבא שאול *Abba Shaul* is teaching. Everybody agrees that it's the
ניזק *nizak*'s carcass but אבא שאול *Abba Shaul* is teaching the same
teaching we had over here that it's the מזיק *mazik*'s responsibility to
bring it out of the pit. responsibility to make the bring the
carcass to, you know, the town so that it could be sold
and the ניזק can go ahead and get some money for it.
So the גמרא Gemara says היכי דמי, heichi dami, let's understand the
case, says the גמרא. Gemara, אילימא דבבירא שויא זוזא ואגודא שויא ארבעה,
Ilima d'be beira shavei zuza ve'aguda shavei arba'ah, כי טרח בדידיה טרח.
ki tarach bididiah tarach. The גמרא Gemara says,
I don't get it. If at the bottom of the well it's
worth a dollar, and when you schlep it to the top of
the well it's worth four dollars, right? Because somebody will say, yeah,
I'll buy it for you from
a dollar because they would have to, you know, transport it, bring
it from the bottom of the well, right? So okay. So and
if you were to bring it at the top of the well,
they would be willing to pay four dollars. So if that's the
scenario, so then the גמרא Gemara says, I don't understand who cares
who's doing it, right? Because in that case, if I was the
מזיק, if you said I didn't have a responsibility to bring it
to the top, I owe the guy ninety-nine dollars. Now I go
ahead, I schlep it to the top, right? Now I owe the
guy ninety-six dollars. So I'm just benefiting myself. So who cares whether
you say I have to bring it to the top and then
we figure out how much I owe, ninety-six, or I don't have
to bring it to the top and it's only worth a dollar
and I then have to pay ninety-nine? So either way it's a
difference, you know, in one case I only pay ninety-six because I
exerted three dollars of effort, and in the other case I pay
ninety-nine and I didn't exert three dollars of effort. Who cares whose
responsibility it is? So אמר ליה, amar leih, he said to him,
look, צריכא דבבירא שויא זוזא ואגודא נמי שויא זוזא. tzricha d'be beira
shavei zuza ve'aguda nami shavei zuza. It's a scenario where, even though
logically it's true that it should be worth more once it's brought
to the top of the well, the case is is that, you
know, people don't, you know, will pay the same whether it's at
the bottom of the well or the top. So the גמרא Gemara
says, ומי איכא כי האי גוונא? u'mi ika ki hai gavna?
Does that ever happen? Like, you know, obviously people are businessmen, they'll
factor in the transport into the cost of the item. So the
גמרא Gemara, says, אין, in, yes, דאמרי אינשי, de'amri inshi, people say,
כשורא במתא בזוזא כשורא בדברא בזוזא. kashura be'mata be'zuza kashura be'dabra be'zuza.
If you want to go ahead and try to buy a beam
in the city, it'll cost you a dollar, and if you want
to go ahead and buy it out in the, you know, out
in the village, it'll, you know, out in the field, it'll also
cost you a dollar, even though, you know, you need to schlep
it into the city. Again, doesn't really explain it because how would
it be that you would not factor in, you know, the cost
of transportation, but we do know sometimes when you put in effort,
you do not necessarily realize, you know, your investment in the increased
price of the object, like when people make home improvements, you know,
the amount that it costs to make the home improvement does not
usually realize it in the resale value of the home to the
full degree. Okay, so basically what the גמרא Gemara is saying is
yes, it does matter. We are going to say that the מזיק
has a responsibility, and even though that will reduce the, might reduce
the מזיק's debt because it's only going to be computed by the
difference, okay, it might not reduce it by as much as the
effort he expended. So he might expend three dollars worth of effort
to bring it to the top of the well, but it's only
going to reduce his debt by a dollar. Okay, so it is
important to determine who has a responsibility to bring this thing to
a place where it could be sold. Fine. So now we have
concluded the principle that פחת נבילה דניזק, that the מזיק pays only
for the damage and he does not own the damaged object, he
only pays for the damage that he that he, you know, did.
And although, again, he might have a responsibility to help bring the
damaged object to a place where it could be sold. All right,
so that's the very important principle that you pay just for the
damage. You don't buy, it's not you break it, you buy it.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר שמואל, amar Shmuel, now
we're going to have an interesting contrast. Said שמואל, Shmuel, אין שמין
לא לגנב ולא לגזלן אלא לנזיקין. ein shamin lo le'ganav ve'lo le'gazlan
ela le'nizikin.
This idea of שמין, shamin, of assessing the difference between how it
was worth and how it's worth now and you pay the difference,
okay, and you look at the damage incurred, that is only for
נזיקין, nezikin for damages, but not for a גנב ganav and a
גזלן, gazlan, a thief
and a burglar. If I go ahead and I steal your your
ten thousand dollar car, okay, and then a tree falls on it
and it destroys and now it's worth a hundred dollars, okay, it's
not that I say, well, I owe you nine thousand nine hundred
dollars, take your car back. No, I owe you the full ten
thousand dollars. This whole principle of פחת נבילה, that the original owner
keeps the ownership of the object, that's by נזק, it's not by
גניבה וגזילה. gneiva ve'gzeila. And the reason for this makes an enormous
amount of sense, and תוספות Tosafot explains why. Because in one case,
I didn't take possession of your object, I just broke it, okay?
I just broke it. It was your object, I made it worthless,
I did a damage, I pay for the damage I did. So
your cow was worth a hundred, now it's worth ten, I damaged
your cow ninety, I owe you ninety dollars. If I steal your
cow, however I took the whole cow. That act of גניבה geneva
or גזילה gezeila made me liable $100. Now that I'm liable $100,
I owe you $100 and if the cow dies, okay, I still
owe you conceptually $100. Can I use the dead cow to pay
back? That's another interesting question. This idea that you can pay back
with סובין, subin, does it apply by גניבה geneva or גזילה? gezeila?
Maybe not. Maybe I have to pay you real cash. Okay, because
fundamentally I owe you $100 and it starts with fundamentally I have
to give you back a cow and if not giving you back
a cow, maybe I have to give you back cash. I can't
give you back crap. Okay? Junk. Okay? So that's one possibility. Even
if I could give you back the dead cow, it's still conceptually
as part of payment, it conceptually starts with the idea that I
owe you for the whole cow. I took the cow, I owe
you $100. Now we can discuss what type of objects or money
or whatever you can use to pay back. So that makes an
enormous amount of sense and that is שמואל's Shmuel's teaching. אין שמין
לא לגנב ולא לגזלן. ein shamin lo leganav velo legazlan. When it
comes to גנב ganav and גזלן, gazlan, you start with the idea
that you stole it, you took it, you owe for the full
amount. אלא לנזיקין. ela lenizikin. It's only for נזיקין nezikin that you
look at the differences. ואני אומר, va'ani omer, says שמואל, Shmuel, and
I say, now who's he contrasting himself to? So רש"י Rashi says
he's contrasting himself to a standard practice of the judges. תוספות Tosafot
has a גרסא girsa that he says my father says that and
I say אף לשואל, af leshoel,
even for a borrower, ואבא מודה לי, ve'aba modeh li, and my
father actually did agree to me on that as well. Now, איבעיא
להו, iba'ya lehu, הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, אף לשואל שמין ואבא מודה
לי? af leshoel shamin ve'aba modeh li? Is he saying that a
שואל shoel is like נזיקין nezikin and you focus on the difference
and my father agrees with me? או דילמא, o dilma, or is
he saying הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar,
ואני אומר אף לשואל אין שמין? va'ani omer af leshoel ein shamin?
I say a שואל shoel, is like a גנב ganav and a
גזלן gazlan and you fundamentally pay for the full amount,
ואבא מודה לי, ve'aba modeh li, and my father agrees. Now, the
reason for that is, it gets to a really interesting conceptual question
because by שומרים, shomrim, as we've seen throughout so far, by a
normal שומר, shomer you could understand my negligence caused this thing to
break, it's like I broke it. Okay? And therefore a normal שומר
shomer would be like נזיקין nezikin and I would pay for the
loss of value. And one of the sources we had earlier was
a standard שומר, shomer, יביאהו עד, right? שומר שכר and so on
was exactly that, that a שומר pays for the loss of value.
It's like I damaged it, I'm liable for the damage. But a
שואל, shoel when I borrow it, there's a degree to which I
am taking the object as if it were mine. I'm using it
as if it were mine and therefore I'm responsible to return the
whole object to you. It's not fundamentally something went wrong and therefore
I have to pay it. It started from the moment I borrowed
it that I had a responsibility, it's like it became mine to
return it and therefore that would be like a גנב ganav or
a גזלן gazlan that you would have to pay for the whole
thing. Okay? So that is the logic of that and that's what
we're going to say. Okay? תא שמע דהוא גברא דשאיל נרגא מחבריה.
ta shema dehu gavra desha'il narga mechavreih. A person borrowed like an
axe from his friend. תברה, tavrah, he broke it. אתא לקמיה דרב.
ata lekamei deRav. He came to רב. Rav.
Excuse me, I made a mistake. אבא here I said father, but
I did not mean father because there's another case about אבוה דשמואל.
avuh deShmuel. אבא here means רב, Rav, okay?
So אבא refers here to רב, Rav, okay? So anyway, so רב
Rav says this or whatever and anyway and he, רב, Rav, agrees
to me. So let's see what רב Rav says. תא שמע דהוא
גברא דשאיל נרגא מחבריה תברה אתא לקמיה דרב. ta shema dehu gavra
desha'il narga mechavreih tavrah ata lekamei deRav. He came to רב, Rav,
אמר ליה זיל שלים ליה נרגא מעליא. amar leih zil shalim leih
narga ma'alya. And רב Rav said, "Go pay for a full axe."
Okay? So you see שמע מינה אין שמין. shema mina ein shamin.
So you see that you do not, that שואל shoel is like
גנב ganav and גזלן, gazlan, that you pay for the full amount.
רב Rav said pay for the full, he didn't say pay for
the difference. Okay? So when שמואל Shmuel said אבא agrees to me,
which means רב Rav agrees to me, clearly he meant agrees to
me that and pays the full amount. Okay? שמע מינה אין שמין.
shema mina ein shamin. אדרבה, adarabba, says the גמרא, the opposite. מדאמרי
ליה רב כהנא ורב אסי לרב, mide'amri leih Rav Kahana veRav Assi
leRav, since רב Rav כהנא and רב אסי Rav Assi challenged רב
Rav and said to him דינא הכי? dina hachi? Is that really
the הלכה? halacha Shouldn't you just pay the difference? ושתיק, veshatik, and
רב Rav's was silent. שמע מינה שמין. shema mina shamin. You see
that actually you pay the difference, that שואל shoel is like other
שומרים. shomrim. Okay? Great question. So you have שומרים shomrim and נזיקין
nezikin where you focus on the damage that was done and you
pay for the difference. You have גניבה geneva and גזילה gezeila where
you took the whole object and you pay for the whole object.
And now which side of it does שואל sho'el fall on? Okay?
So רב's Rav statement originally was that it fell on the גניבה
geneva and גזילה, gezeila, but he was challenged and silent. So it
sounds like maybe he conceded that it falls on the נזיקין side.
Okay, so let's see what the גמרא says.
איתמר אמר עולא אמר רבי אלעזר, itmar amar Ulla amar Rabbi Elazar,
שמין לגנב ולגזלן. shamin leganav ulegazlan. You pay for the גנב ganav
and גזלן gazlan actually even different than everything we've been saying. Even
a גנב ganav and גזלן gazlan you pay the difference. רב פפא
אמר אין שמין. Rav Pappa amar ein shamin. רב פפא Rav Pappa
says you don't. Don't assess the difference, pay for the full amount
what שמואל Shmuel was teaching. והלכתא אין שמין, Vehilchisa ein shamin, and
the הלכה halacha, is you do not, לא לגנב ולא לגזלן, lo
leganav velo legazlan,
not for the גנב ganav and not for the גזלן gazlan like
we've been saying, okay, that is you're חייב for the whole object,
אבל לשואל שמין, aval lesho'el shamin, but for the שואל sho'el you
are שמין, shamin, כדרב כהנא ורב אסי, kidRav Kahana veRav Assi, like
רב Rav כהנא and רב אסי, Rav Assi, they challenged רב and
רב was silent. So even though there's a nice logic by a
שואל sho'el that it's like you took it and it became yours
and you're obligated the full amount, we don't say that. We say
by a שואל sho'el, you're borrowing it, it's not yours, and until
something goes wrong, you're not liable, and when something goes wrong you
are liable, and you're liable for the damage, not for the whole
object. Okay, so whether שומרים, shomrim, whether שואל, whether אדם המזיק, adam
hamazik, whether ממון המזיק, mamon hamazik, all those cases are seen as
cases of damage and you pay the difference, and the owner retains
ownership over the object as opposed to גניבה וגזילה, gneiva vegezeila, you
took the object and you're now חייב for the full object. Okay,
that was the teaching of שמואל. Shmuel. Now that we had that
הלכה in the name of עולא Ulla in the name of רבי
אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, we're going to teach another הלכה, another string of
הלכות halachos in the name of עולא אמר רבי אלעזר. Ulla amar
Rabbi Elazar. ואמר עולא אמר רבי אלעזר, V'amar Ulla amar Rabbi Elazar,
שליא שיצא מקצתה ביום ראשון ומקצתה ביום שני. shilya sheyatza miktzasah beyom
rishon umiktzasah beyom sheni. If a woman had a miscarriage and the
afterbirth came out which contained the embryo
and some of it came out while it was Sunday right before
nightfall and the rest after Sunday night. And the relevance here is
when did the majority of the fetus, which was in the sac,
come out, because that's when she would start counting her seven or
14 days for being טומאת לידה, tum'as leida, for being טמאה teme'ah
for having given childbirth. Okay, so here he said עולא Ulla said
in the name of רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, if it came out
some on day one and some on day two, meaning the end
of Sunday, the beginning of Monday, מונין לה מן הראשון. monin lah
min harishon. You start counting the seven or we do 14 to
be safe, the 14 days in case it was a female, 14
days of טומאת לידה tum'as leida starting from Sunday. אמר ליה רבא,
Amar lei Rava, said רבא, Rava, מה דעתך? ma da'atach? לחומרא? lechumra?
Why are you saying start by Sunday? You want to be safe
because maybe she touched something on Sunday and she was טמאה teme'ah
on Sunday? חומרא דאתי לידי קולא הוא. chumra de'asi lidei kula hu.
It'll lead to a leniency. דקא מיטהרס לה מראשון, de'ka mitaheras lah
merishon, because you're going to count the 14 days starting Sunday, but
the 14 days might only be starting on Monday, so if you
don't know which day the childbirth actually was seen to have occurred,
you should have to play it safe both ways. אלא אמר רבא,
Ela amar Rava, so רבא Rava actually pushes back on this teaching
and says,
לחוש חוששת, lokhush chosheshas, from starting day one she's concerned that she
might be טמאה, teme'ah, and if she touches something it's טמא. tamei.
ממנא לא ממניא אלא לשני. mimna lo mamania ela lesheni. But she
only starts counting the 14 days to know when her טומאה tum'ah
is going to end from Monday. מאי קא משמע לן? Mai kamashma
lan? So the גמרא says, what חידוש chiddush is any of this?
דאין מקצת שליא בלא ולד. de'ein miktzas shilya belo velad. What it's
teaching you is even if a little part of the sac comes
out on Sunday, we're concerned that it
has some of the fetus in it if the fetus here, the
assumption is, is dissolved, and if it has some, we're concerned it
has the majority. Because if we were to say it would be
possible that some of the sac came out and none of the
fetus was in it, then we would not be concerned that there
was a majority and that the childbirth had started from Sunday. The
only reason we're concerned childbirth might be started Sunday is because we
start by assuming some of the fetus definitely came out with the
sac on Sunday and therefore we're concerned it's a majority. So that's
the חידוש. chiddush. The חידוש chiddush is that we start by saying
definitely some of the fetus came out with the sac on Sunday.
So the גמרא says, תנינא, but we already taught that. שליא שיצא
מקצתה אסורה באכילה. shilya sheyatza miktzasah asurah ba'akhilah. Okay,
if an animal, this, the amniotic sac came out a little bit
and then the animal was שחט shechted while a little of the
amniotic sac came out, then what's in the amniotic sac is forbidden
because normally we would say the שחיטה shechitah on the animal would
permit what was in the womb of the animal, and if the
animal had a fetus and so on, but since we're assuming that
some of the amniotic sac came out and there definitely was some
of the animal there, we're assuming it might be the majority, so
therefore the whole thing is going to be forbidden. אסורה באכילה. asurah
ba'akhilah. סימן ולד באשה סימן ולד בבהמה. siman velad be'isha siman velad
bibeheimah.
The amniotic sac is an indication that there is birth, whether for
a woman or for an animal. So that shows you, says the
גמרא, that we say that definitely some of the animal came out
with the sac, because if we didn't say that, then we would
be lenient and we would not have to be
concerned to make forbidden what was in the amniotic sac, because maybe
none of the animal came out and maybe it was permissible when
the mother was שחט. shechted. So the גמרא says no, אם ממתניתין
הוה אמינא, im mimasnisin hava amina, if it was just for that,
I would have said יש מקצת
שליא בלא ולד, yesh miktzas shilya belo velad, it's possible that when
that sac came out, there was no animal in it, so then
why are we saying... Never mind that the animal that then is
found afterwards inside of it is the fetus is forbidden, וגזירה מקצת
אטו כולה קא משמע לן. ugzeira miktzat atu kula ka mashma lan.
Nevertheless, I'm not going to allow that case of eating from what's
in the amniotic sac, you know, when you שחט shecht the animal
even though it's possible nothing was in what came out when the
animal was shechted, because it'll lead to permitting it cases when a
lot came out or the majority or all of it came out
and so on. So therefore we just have to forbid it when
any part of that sac comes out but it doesn't prove whether
we say definitely some of the fetus was in it or wasn't
it. Some of those cases are going to be a problem, we
have to forbid all of them. But in our case, you know,
we need to know whether you start counting on Sunday or Monday
and there's a חידוש chidush here that we have to be concerned
already on Sunday. Okay. ואמר עולא אמר רבי אלעזר v’amar Ulla amar
Rabbi Elazar says עולא Ulla in the name of רבי אלעזר, Rabbi
Elazar, top of י"א עמוד ב’, another teaching. בכור שנטרף בתוך שלושים
יום, bechor shenitraf betoch shloshim yom, if you had a בכור bechor
firstborn son and something happened, you know, was attacked by an animal
and or whatever, attacked by people and it became a טריפה, treifa,
you know, some wound that made it that meant that the boy
was definitely going to die. Okay, within the thirty days, so before
he became obligated in the מצוה mitzvah of פדיון הבן, pidyon haben,
אין פודין אותו, ein podin oso, then when day thirty rolls around
you don't do פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. Even though when he was
born he was totally healthy and he could have lived and even
though he's still alive, this is how תוספות understands it on day
thirty, since he's now a טריפה, treifa, even though clearly it was
due to outside forces, he's not considered to be a full like
living person and therefore you do not do פדיון הבן. pidyon haben.
וכן תני רמי בר חמא vechen tani Rami bar Chama מתוך שנאמר
פדה תפדה mitoch shene’emar padoh tifdeh because the פסוק says you shall
surely redeem. יכול אפילו נטרף בתוך שלושים יום, yachol afilu nitraf betoch
shloshim yom, maybe you would even redeem a boy that became a
טריפה treifa during the first thirty days? תלמוד לומר אך חלק, talmud
lomar ach cholak, however,
that there are cases you don't do it. Okay, that's that teaching.
ואמר עולא אמר רבי אלעזר, v’amar Ulla amar Rabbi Elazar, a lot
of things with animals and, you know, births and so on. בהמה
גסה ניקנית במשיכה, behema gassa nikneit bemeshicha,
so now you have a large animal like a cow, you can
take possession of it by drawing it near you, משיכה. meshicha. Okay,
that's another teaching. והנן תנן במסירה, ve’anan tnan bemesira, one minute in
קידושין Kiddushin we said that you take possession of a cow or
horse or whatever by handing over the reins. So how is he
saying only by pulling it to you? הוא דאמר כי האי תנא,
hu d’amar ki hai tanna, he teaches like the other תנא, דתניא
וחכמים אומרים זו וזו במשיכה, detanya v’Chachamim omrim zu v’zu bemeshicha,
know that even a, not only a sheep you do משיכה, meshicha,
you pull it, and a goat but even a cow and a
horse by משיכה. meshicha. That's his teaching. רבי שמעון אומר זו וזו
בהגבהה, Rabbi Shimon omer zu v’zu behagbaha, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
both, actually both a sheep, goat, and also like horse and a
cow only by lifting up. And the גמרא discusses how do you
lift up a cow? Okay. ואמר עולא, v’amar Ulla,
yet another teaching of עולא Ulla in the name of רבי אלעזר.
Rabbi Elazar. אמר רבי אלעזר amar Rabbi Elazar האחים שחלקו מה שעליהם
שמין מה שעל בניהם ובנותיהם אין שמין. ha’achim shecholku ma she’aleihem shamin
ma she’al beneihem uvnoteihem ein shamin. You have brothers that have been
living off of an estate, they have yet to divide up the
estate, okay, when it finally comes time to divide up off the
estate, you figure out how much, you know, you assess, you have
them come to בית דין and you assess the value of the
clothes that they're wearing that if they, you know, got those clothes
from the money of the estate and that goes towards how much
they took from the estate when you're figuring everything out about equal
division. But you don't ask them to bring their kids to the
בית דין to assess the clothes that their kids are wearing even
if it was paid for from the estate. Why? Because it is
not considered to be like,
you know, appropriate to be
bringing the
kids, it would not be like respectful to them to have to
schlep all these kids to בית דין to assess the value of
the clothes that they're wearing. So you just figure that everybody is
מוחל. mochel. All right. ומה שעל בניהם ובנותיהם אין שמין. uma she’al
beneihem uvnoteihem ein shamin. אמר רב פפא amar Rav Papa פעמים אף
מה שעליהם אין שמין. pa’amim af ma she’aleihem ein shamin. There are
times that even that what's on them you don't assess, that you
don't like, you know, say, oh you're wearing a thousand dollar Armani
suit and you're only wearing a two hundred dollar suit, so, you
know, you've already taken a thousand dollars from the estate and you've
taken two hundred, there are times you don't say that even for
the brothers themselves. Why? משכחת לה בגדול אחי דניחא להו דלישתמעו מיליה,
meshkachat lah begadol achi denicha lehu delishtame’u milei,
if one of them, the elder brother or somebody acting in that
capacity representing the estate, you know, in various business deals, if there's
been one person that's been doing that and therefore he's been using
estate money like as a clothing allowance, you know, to dress properly
so that he can represent them and get good deals for the
brothers and so on, then he can continue to keep those clothes
and you assume because the brothers were מוחל mochel they were okay
that he was using the estate money even though he wound up
taking more money out of the estate than they did, that was
important for all of their benefit. Okay. ואמר עולא סידו אמר רבי
אלעזר, v’amar Ulla sidu amar Rabbi Elazar, שומר שמסר לשומר פטור. shomer
shemassar l’shomer patur. Now this is a whole סוגיא sugya in בבא
מציעא, Bava Metzia, but again it's a teaching of עולא Ulla in
the name of רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. If a שומר hands over
to another שומר, he's פטור, patur, meaning that does not make him
liable for damages. Okay, so if ראובן, Fred gave something to ראובן
to watch, ראובן asks שמעון, hey would you watch this for me,
I'm watching this for... for Fred, the giving it over to שמעון
*Shimon* does not make ראובן *Reuven* liable. ראובן *Reuven* is still liable
for whatever he would have normally been liable for. If he's a
שומר חנם *shomer chinam*, he'll be liable for פשיעה *pshiah*, if he's
a שומר שכר *shomer sachar*, גניבה ואבידה *geneiva v'aveida*. Okay, but he's
not more liable for handing it over to שמעון *Shimon*. ולא מבעיא
*v'lo mibaya* שומר חנם שמסר לשומר שכר דעלויי עלייה לשמירתו *shomer chinam
shemasar l'shomer sachar de'iluyei alyah l'shmirato*, obviously, it goes without saying that
if ראובן *Reuven* was a שומר חנם *shomer chinam* and he paid
שמעון *Shimon* to watch it for him, and that would have ensured
logically even better שמירה *shmira* because you know, שמעון *Shimon* is being
paid and he's going to work harder and he's also going to
be more responsible if something goes wrong, so you can assume it
would be even better, certainly in that case ראובן *Reuven* did nothing
wrong that he raised the level of שמירה *shmira*. אלא אפילו שומר
שכר שמסר לשומר חנם *ella afillu shomer sachar shemasar l'shomer chinam*, even
if ראובן *Reuven* was a שומר שכר *shomer sachar* and he gave
it to שמעון *Shimon* to do it for free, and you could
assume that if שמעון *Shimon* is doing it for free he's not
going to do as good of a job, דהשתא גרעיה לשמירתו *dehashtah
gardei l'shmirato*, now שמעון *Shimon* is going to do a lesser job,
נמי פטור *nami patur*. ראובן *Reuven* is exempt, he doesn't incur liability
for handing it over to שמעון *Shimon*. Okay, now as a שומר
שכר *shomer sachar*, he's still going to be חייב *chayav* in גניבה
ואבידה *geneiva v'aveida*. Okay, he doesn't get off the hook, he doesn't
walk away, okay, but he does not incur any liability for handing
it over to שמעון *Shimon*.
Okay, that is the teaching. Why? שהרי מסר לבן דעת *sheharei masar
l'ben da'at*, because at the end of the day שמעון *Shimon* is
an adult and a responsible person, so you know, he did not
do anything wrong or negligent by asking
שמעון *Shimon* to watch it, and you know, his level of liability
remains the level it always was.
That's עולא Ulla *Ulla* in the name of רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar*.
רבא Rava, *Rava* however disagrees. רבא אמר שומר שמסר לשומר חייב *Rava
amar shomer shemasar l'shomer chayav*. No, actually if ראובן *Reuven* gives it
to שמעון *Shimon*, the act of giving it is an act of
negligence or violating the terms of your agreement or we'll see other
possibilities, and therefore actually he is going to be חייב *chayav* if
something goes wrong, and here חייב *chayav* means חייב *chayav* even if
an אונס *ones* happened. Even if, you know, some accident happens, nobody's
fault, the thing broke, as soon as you shirked your responsibility that
you accepted on yourself to watch it, you are now liable for
anything that goes wrong. Sort of like תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס *techilato
b'fshiah v'sof b'ones*. Okay. ולא מבעיא שומר שכר שמסר לשומר חנם דגרעיה
לשמירתו *v'lo mibaya shomer sachar shemasar l'shomer chinam dehashtah gardei l'shmirato*. It
goes without saying that if ראובן *Reuven* was a שומר שכר *shomer
sachar* and he gave it to שמעון *Shimon* and שמעון *Shimon* was
a שומר חנם *shomer chinam* that he actually, you know, made, you
could expect that it was going to be watched in a less
careful way, certainly that was an act of negligence on ראובן *Reuven*'s
part, גרעיה לשמירתו *gardei l'shmirato*. אלא אפילו שומר חנם שמסר לשומר שכר
*ella afillu shomer chinam shemasar l'shomer sachar*, even if ראובן *Reuven* was
a שומר חנם *shomer chinam* and he now has שמעון *Shimon* doing
it as a שומר שכר *shomer sachar*, so he could actually be
saying, I actually hired somebody who I could expect would do a
better job than me and therefore what did I do wrong? No,
חייב *chayav*, you have violated the terms, you have been negligent, you
are going to be liable if anything goes wrong. Why? דאמר ליה
*de'amar lei*, because the owner who gave you this object to watch
could say, את מהימנת לי בשבועה האי לא מהימנת לי בשבועה *at
meimnat li bishvua hai lo meimnat li bishvua*. I trusted you, and
therefore that means that if something happened to the object you would
make a שבועה *shvua* to attest to what happened to the object,
and I had implicitly agreed that I would accept your שבועה *shvua*.
I never agreed I would accept שמעון *Shimon*'s שבועה *shvua*. So if
something happens from it now, I just, you know, any שבועה *shvua*
he makes to me is just going to be rejected out of
hand. And therefore I'm going to have to just assume that it
was negligence. Now if said that way it's only a question of
does a שבועה *shvua* have to be, you know, who can be
believed? If there were witnesses, if ראובן *Reuven* happened to be around
so he could directly testify with a שבועה *shvua*, that would seem
to negate those concerns. But in בבא מציעא *Bava Metzia* another issue
for why שומר שמסר לשומר חייב *shomer shemasar l'shomer chayav* is given,
which is basically, which is, you know, אין רצוני שיהא פקדוני ביד
אחר *ein ritzoni she'yehei pikdoni b'yad acher*. I never agreed that anybody
else would watch it. You fundamentally violated the terms, I wanted you
to watch it, nobody else, period. I don't care if you tell
me he would have done a better job, not a better job,
that was going against your responsibility, and you shirked your responsibility and
therefore you're liable. Okay. ואמר עולא
*v'amar Ulla*, we'll do one more, says עולא *Ulla*, אמר עולא אמר
רבי אלעזר הלכתא גובין מן העבדים *amar Ulla amar Rabbi Elazar hilchata
govin min ha'avadim*. You can collect from עבדים *avadim*, which basically means
that,
that, slaves are like קרקע karka *karka*, are like land, and therefore
if there's a debt against somebody, then, you know, the creditors have
lien on the person's real estate, so this seems to say they
also have lien on the person's עבדים *avadim*, which means if the
person sells his עבדים *avadim* or sells his, you know, same way
if he sells his real estate, they can be, the debt can
be collected from them. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, אמר ליה רב
נחמן לעולא *amar lei Rav Nachman l'Ulla*, רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* said
to עולא *Ulla*, אמר רבי אלעזר אפילו ביתמי *amar Rabbi Elazar afillu
b'yasmi*? Did he really say even from orphans? Which really is, you
know, תוספות *Tosafot* says any discussion here of orphans it's really not
different from that about לקוחות *lakuchos*. other parties who buy it. Really?
Did he really say that you can collect from slaves and you
have a lien on slaves and you can collect from somebody that's
not the original debtor himself, whether from orphans or even or from
purchasers? Did he really say that? So, so לא מיניה. minei? So
he said, "No, no, no, I didn't mean that. I meant that
you can collect from slaves if they're still in the possession of
the original debtor." So he said back, מיניה? From him, אפילו מגלימא
דעל כתפיה? afilu miglima d'al katfei? You can even take the shirt
off his back! Not literally, but whatever. But obviously you can take,
the idea is normally the world is divided into קרקע karka and
מטלטלין. metaltelin. מטלטלין metaltelin are chattel, קרקע is real estate. For the
debtor himself, you can collect from any of his property. But if
you want to collect from somebody that's not the debtor because they
have a lien, because the debtor sold his property or he died
and his heirs have it, that's only real estate, and then we
have to decide which bucket does slaves go into? Do they go
into the chattel or do they go into the property category? So
now that he's saying this idea that you can collect from slaves
means from the debtor himself, well that's obvious, you can collect from
anything from the debtor himself.
So no, so then we're going to reverse a second time, הכא
במאי עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan, what are we talking about? שעשאו אפותיקי.
she'asao apotiki. That you actually made the slave an אפותיקי, apotiki, which
is basically like you designated a lien, an explicit lien on the
slave himself. It wasn't just generic liens that get created automatically on
my real estate, but that the slave you specifically said there will
be a lien on this slave. Okay, so now what עולא is
revising the statement of רב אלעזר, Rav Elazar, it sounded like he
was saying slaves are like real estate, there are liens. Okay, now
he under pressure he's revising it to say basically slaves don't have
liens, they are like chattel, but if you make an explicit אפותיקי
apotiki lien on it, then you can collect from it. Okay, כי
דרבא, ki d'Rava, like רבא, דאמר רבא עשה עבדו אפותיקי ומכרו בעל
חוב גובה הימנו. d'amar Rava asa avdo apotiki umacharo ba'al chov goveh
heimenu. That if you went ahead and you made your slave an
אפותיקי, apotiki, you put a lien on it, then you could go
ahead and collect from it from a third party, from a purchaser
or from an heir. Okay, however, so now you'll say, okay again,
that's obvious, you made an explicit lien. But it's not obvious because
it does not work by normal chattel. שור אפותיקי ומכרו אין בעל
חוב גובה הימנו. shor apotiki umacharo ein ba'al chov goveh heimenu. מאי
טעמא האי אית ליה קלא והאי לית ליה קלא. mai ta'ama hai
it lei kala v'hai leit lei kala. No, because at the end
of the day, right, the slave is still like real estate in
that it's more public what, like people know what the slaves are
and if you make a lien on a slave, people will know,
oh,
ראובן's slave, that person over there, there's a lien on him and
therefore if somebody buys the slave they will- it's buyer beware. They'll
know that there's a lien on it. Okay, slaves are still people
and therefore they're individuals and they're known and they're known that they
have liens on them, which ones have liens, which ones don't, and
therefore it's only fair to allow these liens to work if the
people that purchase the
property can protect themselves. So therefore there's by default a lien on
real estate and that's something that's considered to be generally known and
knowable, that's why there are also documents
about
it and therefore the purchasers of real estate can protect themselves or
be aware what they're getting into when they buy real estate. And
therefore by a slave by default there aren't liens, but if you
make a lien that will work because it'll become well enough known
and people can protect themselves or be aware, whereas a lien made
explicitly on something like a cow, that will not take effect because
nobody knows which cow has a lien and therefore nobody can protect
themselves. Okay, and we will continue with this discussion tomorrow.